Finding aid for Taylor family papers, 1827-1908
Bentley Historical Library
Taylor family papers
1827-1908
Bentley Historical Library
Taylor family.
86227 Aa 2
4 linear feet
7.3 MB (online)
Albion, Michigan, family. Papers of Barton Stout Taylor, Methodist clergyman; diaries of his wife, Elizabeth Gurney Taylor, detailing her everyday activities; papers of Ralph Wendell Taylor, alumnus of University of Michigan and teacher in the Philippine Islands, 1901-1908; and other family materials.
The collection was the gift of Clarence Wochholtz (donor no. 578 ) and came to the library in 1938.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Barton Stout Taylor, son of Philo Taylor and Theodosia Octavia Stout, was born in Bloomfield, Ontario County, New York, May 19, 1820. In 1827, the family moved to Plymouth Township in Wayne County, Michigan. He graduated from a Medical College in Cleveland in 1845. That same year, he married Marietta Rowland. There were five children born to the couple. One of them was Fred M. Taylor, professor political economy at the University of Michigan. Marietta Taylor died in 1857.
Barton Stout Taylor practiced medicine for a time, but then felt impelled to enter the ministry. As a Methodist clergyman, he would serve in various Michigan communities. In 1866, he married Elizabeth Ann Gurney. Eight children were born of this union, including Ralph W. Taylor and Hartley W. Taylor. Upon retirement in 1883, Taylor settled in Albion, Michigan where he became college librarian. Barton S. Taylor died February 22, 1898.
Ralph Wendell Taylor, one of the sons of Barton and Elizabeth Taylor, was a teacher in the Philippines in the first decade of the Twentieth Century. He was stationed first in La Union Province and then in Tarlac.
Hartley W. Taylor, another son, succeeded his father as Albion College librarian.
The Taylor family papers consist of correspondence Barton Stout Taylor, Methodist clergyman; diaries of his wife, Elizabeth Gurney Taylor, detailing her everyday activities; papers of Ralph Wendell Taylor, alumnus of University of Michigan and teacher in the Philippine Islands, 1901-1908; and other family materials. The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Family miscellaneous, Barton S. Taylor; Elizabeth Gurney Taylor; and Other family members.
Albion (Calhoun County, Mich.); Antislavery movements -- United States.; Clergy -- Michigan -- Albion (Calhoun County); Houghton (Mich.); Justices of the peace -- Michigan -- Wayne County.; Michigan -- Social life and customs -- 1851-1860.; Michigan -- Social life and customs -- 1861-1870.; Michigan -- Social life and customs -- 1871-1880.; Michigan -- Social life and customs -- 1881-1890.; Michigan -- Social life and customs -- 19th century.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Public schools -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Saginaw (Mich.); Spouses of clergy -- Michigan -- Albion (Calhoun County); Temperance -- United States.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Wayne County (Mich.); Women -- Michigan -- Albion (Calhoun County); Women's rights -- United States.; Women -- Suffrage -- United States.; Account books.; Diaries.; Sermons.; Digital file formats.; Ann Arbor Academy.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; Literary Circle (Saint Clair, Mich.); Methodist Episcopal Church -- Michigan.; Taylor, Philo.; Taylor, Barton S., 1820-; Taylor, Elizabeth Ann Gurney.; Taylor, Ralph Wendell.; Taylor, Wallace.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is a mixture of incoming letters. Prior to 1890, most of the letters were addressed to Barton S. Taylor from his children, to his wife Elizabeth, and to other members of the family. These letters concern family matters and church activities. After Barton's death, and dating between 1901 and 1908, the letters are of Ralph W. Taylor to his mother in which he described his life in the Philippines, problems of being an American teacher, and giving his comments on the American colonial administration. Although nonpolitical in character, Taylor's letters reveal an opinionated man, a person not afraid of speaking his mind. Consequently, his letters make for interesting and provocative reading.
  - circa 1827-1908, 28 folders (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - And incomplete, Undated (Box 1)
  - Letters to Ralph Taylor, Undated (Box 1)
  - Family Letter Transcriptions
    (Original letters are available in the collection.)
    - Disc 1 of 2, 1828-1908
      (Includes transcribed letters by Hartley-Frances Taylor, other Taylor family members, and transcribers notes.)
    - Disc 2 of 2, 1901-1908
      (Contains transcribed letters by Ralph W. Taylor.)
- Family miscellaneous
  - School papers of members of the Taylor family (Box 1)
  - Sunday school and public school report cards and exams (Box 1)
  - Vital statistics (Box 1)
  - Poetry (Box 1)
  - Accounts kept by Barton S. Taylor as trustee of the estate of Philo Taylor; also justice of the peace records of Philo Taylor (Box 1)
- Barton S. Taylor
  The Barton S. Taylor series includes articles and other writings on such topics as anti-slavery, phrenology, temperance, and Lake Superior and Upper Peninsula Michigan. This series also contains sermons on books of the Bible and other doctrinal expositions.
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences (Box 1)
  - Articles and other writings
    - Albion (Box 1)
    - General folder no. 1:
      - Anti-slavery (Box 1)
      - General Fisk (Box 1)
      - Death of Lincoln (Box 1)
    - General folder no. 2:
      - Cause of disease, 1842 (Box 1)
      - Letter to Dr. McCosh (Box 1)
      - Phrenology (Box 1)
      - View of the Methodist Episcopal Church in the South (Box 1)
    - General folder no. 3:
      - Literary Circle, Saint Clair, 1864 (Box 1)
      - East Saginaw Lodge (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous (author unknown) (Box 1)
    - General folder no. 4: Temperance and third party (Box 1)
    - Lake Superior Region (Box 1)
    - Philosophy of Energy, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - The relation of metaphysics to science, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - "Modes of Investigation" (incomplete) and "The Uniformity and Diversity of Human Nature" (incomplete) (Box 2)
    - "Classes of Properties" (incomplete) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous:
      - The Present Status of the Doctrine of the Conservation of Energy (Box 2)
      - Causal Relations (Box 2)
      - The Comparative Merits of the Sensational and Transcendental Philosophies (Box 2)
      - The General Rules of Moral Duty Innate in the Human Mind (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - School papers and early articles of B.S. Taylor (some written at Ann Arbor Academy) (Box 2)
  - Sermons (B.S. Taylor) on books of the Bible
    - Daniel; Deuteronomy (Box 2)
    - Ephesians (Box 2)
    - Exodus; Ezekiel (Box 2)
    - Ecclesiastes (Box 2)
    - Galatians (Box 2)
    - Romans, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Ruth; Thessalonians (Box 2)
    - I Timothy (Box 2)
    - II Timothy; Zechariah (Box 2)
    - Micah; Numbers; I Peter (Box 2)
    - I Peter (Box 2)
    - II Peter; Philippians (Box 2)
    - Proverbs (Box 2)
    - Psalms, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Revelations, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Joshua; Jude (Box 2)
    - I and II Kings (Box 2)
    - Luke, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Malachi; Mark (Box 2)
    - Hebrews, chapters 1-9 (Box 3)
    - Hebrews, chapters 10-13 (Box 3)
    - Matthews, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Isaiah
      - Chapters 1-26 (Box 3)
      - Chapters 40-56 (Box 3)
      - Chapters 57-63 (Box 3)
    - James (Box 3)
    - Jeremiah; Job (Box 3)
    - John, 6 folders (Box 3)
    - Acts (Box 3)
    - Colossians, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - I Corinthians, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - II Corinthians (Box 3)
  - Sermons and addresses (B.S. Taylor) on miscellaneous subjects
    - Folder no. 1
      - The Foundation of Belief (Box 3)
      - Physical Education (Box 3)
      - The Revelation of Natural Theology to Revealed (Box 3)
      - Social Purity (Box 3)
      - Teleiotic Ideas (Box 3)
    - Folder no. 2
      - "He that Humbleth Himself Shall Be Exalted" (Box 3)
      - What is Conscience (Box 3)
      - Can it be done? (Box 3)
      - Pray Alway (Box 3)
      - "Likewise Reckon Ye Yourselves Dead Unto Sin..." (Box 3)
    - Folder no. 3
      - Public morals in Houghton (Box 3)
      - Shall we organize a temperance political party? (Box 3)
      - A temperance political party (Box 3)
      - Who inhabited America before its discovery by Columbus? (Box 3)
      - Wine Mockers (Box 3)
    - Folder no. 4
      - The Duty of Temperance men at this crisis (Box 3)
      - The Harmony between science and revelation (Box 3)
      - The Relation between home life and the Sunday school (Box 3)
    - Folder no. 5
      - Female suffrage (Box 3)
      - The Future of America (Box 3)
      - The Great Conflict of the Years to Come (Box 3)
      - Ministerial Unsuccess and its causes (Box 3)
      - The Moral condition of infants (Box 3)
    - Folder no. Fragmentary (Box 3)
- Elizabeth Gurney Taylor
  The Elizabeth Gurney Taylor series includes twelve volumes of diaries (1854-1861, 1863, and 1865-1886) detailing her routine daily activities, people she met, school work, family affairs, church attendance, the weather, her health, and a few comments on current events. The diary entries are particularly concerned with Taylor's spiritual life. Elizabeth Gurney's diaries were written at the Gurney family home in Centreville, Mich. (1854-1857) and from the Michigan State Normal School in Ypsilanti, Mich. (1858-1861). An 1857 trip to the northeastern U.S. is described. After her marriage to Taylor the family moved quite often as Barton Taylor was sent to different churches. After a description of an 1863 trip from Detroit to Lake Superior, the diaries were written in Saginaw, Mich. (1865-1866), Houghton, Mich. (1866-1869), Mount Clemens, Mich. (1869-1872), Utica, Mich. (1872-1875), Corunna, Mich. (1875-1876), Dundee, Mich. (1876-1877), Mount Clemens once again (1877-1879), Houghton again (1879-1881), Escanaba, Mich. (1882-1883), and Albion, Mich. (1883-1886).
  - Diaries, 12 volumes
    - April 4, 1854-January 23, 1855 (Box 4)
      (folder 1)
    - January 24, 1855-September 9, 1855 (Box 4)
      (folder 2)
    - September 10, 1855-September 13, 1857 (Box 4)
      (folder 3)
    - September 14, 1857-June 16, 1858 (Box 4)
      (folder 4)
    - June 17, 1858-November 30, 1858 (Box 4)
      (folder 5)
    - December 1, 1858-October 9, 1859 (Box 4)
      (folder 6)
    - October 10, 1859-May 31, 1860 (Box 4)
      (folder7)
    - June 1, 1860-October 12, 1861 (Box 4)
      (folder 8)
    - October 12, 1861-February 16, 1864 (Box 4)
      (folder 9)
    - February 17, 1864-December 31, 1866 (Box 4)
      (folder 10)
    - January 1, 1867-August 18, 1870 (Box 4)
      (folder 11)
    - August 19, 1870-November 25, 1886 (Box 4)
      (folder 12)
    - Reminiscence and excerpts from diary (Box 4)
      (folder 13)
  - Autograph book (Box 4)
    (folder 14)
  - Account book, 1902-1906 (Box 4)
    (folder no. 15)
- Other family members
  - Wallace Taylor essays (Box 4)
    (the authorship of one of the volumes is uncertain)
    (folders 16-17)
  - Hartley Wright Taylor
    - Diary transcription (Box 4)
      (with notes by Frances Taylor)
    - Letters exchanged with Fanny E. Elder, 1903-1904 (Box 4)
      (she was writing from Kalamazoo, he from Montana; the letters were both an introduction to each other and the beginning of a courtship; Hartley's letters are descriptive of the Bitterroot Valley in Montana.)